Guide to the Landon family papers 1977.025
Brooklyn Historical Society
Landon family papers
Bulk, 1718-1864
1665-1864, bulk 1718-1864
1977.025
Brooklyn Historical Society
2.5 Linear feet in 5 manuscript boxes
The Landon family papers relate principally to Jared Landon (died circa 1815) and to Henry Landon (died 1866) in their capacities as county judges, estate executors, and landholders. The Landons were residents of Cutchogue, part of the town of Southold in Suffolk County on the eastern end of Long Island, and the bulk of the collection concerns that area. Other Landons, such as Jared's father Samuel (circa 1700-1782), and other New York areas are represented in the collection, though to a much lesser extent. The collection is rich with legal and financial documents that can provide insight into social, economic, cultural, and political aspects of Suffolk County in the late eigtheenth century and first half of the nineteenth century. Document types include inventories, vendue (auction) accounts, day books, ledgers, promissory notes, court orders, trespasses and other court-related documents, land indentures and transfers, town meeting notices and resolutions, and more. The collection also holds substantive correspondence on legal, financial, personal, and political matters, including those related to the Democratic Party in Southold in the late 1820s-1840s. Documents concerning the American Revolution and the British occupation of New York, including the imprisonment of Jared Landon, are in the collection. References to African-Americans appear throughout the collection, including in account books and court cases.
Conkling, David, d. 1787?
Landon family
Landon, Henry
Landon, Jared
Landon, Samuel, ca. 1700-1782?
Conditions Governing Access note
Open to researchers without restriction.
Related Archival Materials note
The Landons' stay in Provost prison is referenced in the John Fell diary, held by Brooklyn Historical Society (collection 1974.225).
An undated document related to Henry Landon can be found in the Middagh family papers (collection 1974.179). This document records the terms of sale of property mortgaged by Isaac Conklin and George L. Conklin to Landon (property unspecified).
Brooklyn Historical Society holds account books of David Conkling, a subject of the Landon papers (collection 1974.073).
Col. Archibald Hamilton, the subject of wartime complaints in the Landon papers, is likely the same Hamilton found in the John Kissam papers held by Brooklyn Historical Society (collection 1974.133).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Landon papers were acquired in 1866 from the estate of Henry Landon. The papers were selected by Rev. Epher Whitaker, a Suffolk County counsellor for the Long Island Historical Society.
Arrangement note
The Landon family papers were found to be only roughly organized at the beginning of processing in 2010, with a substantial portion of the collection categorized as miscellaneous or other catch-all term. There was no indication that the material was still in its original order. Consequently, the material was substantially rearranged, and a series structure and folder titles imposed, by the processing archivist.
The collection is organized in the following series: Series 1 - Legal Files; Series 2 - Correspondence; Series 3 - Financial Records; Series 4 - Miscellaneous.
Users of the collection should be aware that it is likely that documents on some matters will be found in various series, and in various folders within series. For example, documents related to estate work will be found in all of the series. Also, Henry Landon commonly used sheets of paper for multiple purposes (e.g., calculations, drafts of agreements, estate notes, etc.) and multiple matters. Generally, these documents could be placed within one series despite their multiple uses. Documents with "mixed content" that ranged across series in significant ways were placed in the Miscellaneous series.
Folders labeled with a date range might also include undated documents.
Scope and Contents note
The Landon family papers are comprised principally of legal and financial documents concerning matters involving Jared and Henry Landon. Most of these matters concerned the Landons in their capacities as justices of the peace in Suffolk County, estate executors, or landholders. Accordingly, the collection has extensive legal files, such as court orders, testimony, trespasses on cases, court decisions, etc. Legal matters were of a criminal, civil, and commercial nature. Financial records include inventories, vendue (auction) account books, day books, ledgers, receipts, promissory notes, invoices, account statements, and the like. Many of the financial records concern the estate of merchant David Conkling. Indentures, mortgages, deeds, wills, and other documents related to land matters are in the collection. The collection also holds substantive correspondence on legal, political, financial, and personal matters. The bulk of the collection concerns Southold, and particularly Cutchogue, in Suffolk County, though some records relate to Kings County, New York City, and elsewhere. Overall, the collection is rich with documents that can provide insight into social, economic, cultural, and political aspects of Suffolk County in the late eighteenth century and first half of the nineteenth century.
The collection includes correspondence and other material from the American Revolution period, including documents related to Jared's imprisonment by the British and Samuel Landon's time as a refugee in Connecticut. References to African-Americans appear throughout the collection, including in account books and court cases. Jared and Henry were politically active in the emerging Democratic Party, and the collection includes material on national and local politics, especially from the late 1820s to the 1840s.
The collection also holds miscellaneous documents dating principally from the 1700s with no clear connection to the Landons. The American Revolution and Indian treaty proceedings are among the several subjects found in these documents. The documents include the journal maintained by Daniel Youngs while he was imprisoned in the Provost of New York during the Revolution.
Bibliographic References
Information on Samuel and Jared Landon's part in the American Revolution can be found in:
Jefferson, Wayland. Southold and its People in the Revolutionary Days. Southold, NY: Long Island Traveler Print, 1932.
Jefferson, Wayland. Cutchogue: Southold's First Colony. New York: Colonial Press, 1940. This book includes transcriptions of some of the correspondence between Jared and Samuel found in this collection.
Reference to the relationship of Jared Landon to David Conkling can be found in: Easter, David M., abstractor. The Wills of Suffolk County, Long Island [New York], Liber A, 1787-1798. Westminster, Maryland: Heritage Books, 2007 (reprint). See page 8, item A-41.
Reference to Henry Landon's marriage can be found in the Long Island Star of October 6, 1819.
Biographical Note
The Landon family papers relate principally to Henry Landon (died 1866) and to his father, Jared Landon (died circa 1815). Other Landons represented in the papers are Samuel Landon (circa 1700-1782), who was the father of Jared, and Samuel Hutchinson Landon (died circa 1843), who was the grandson of Jared and nephew of Henry. Another family relationship relevant to these papers is the marriage in 1819 of Henry to Mehetabel Griffing, the widow of Samuel Griffing.
The Landons were residents of Cutchogue, part of the town of Southold in Suffolk County on the eastern end of Long Island. During the American Revolution, both Samuel and his son Jared were supporters of the rebellion. As a result, during the British occupation of New York, father and son spent some time in prison. After his release, Samuel became a "refugee," fleeing with some family members to Guilford, Connecticut, where he would die in 1782. Jared remained on Long Island.
Samuel, Jared and Henry Landon owned farmland, but also held various Suffolk County and Southold public offices, including county judicial positions that earned them the appellation "Judge." Along with many other legal matters, Jared and Henry were involved, as either surrogate judges or as executors, with the administration of estates. For example, Jared was executor for his brother-in-law, merchant David Conkling, who was imprisoned with the Landons by the British. Henry was executor for Jared's grandson, Samuel H.
Both Jared and Henry represented their district in the New York State Assembly at various times. Henry was active in the local politics of Southold as a member of the emerging Democratic Party.
Conkling, David, d. 1787?; Democratic Party (New York, N.Y.).; Floyd, C. A., (Charles Albert), 1791-1873 -- Correspondence; Huntington, Abel, 1777-1858 -- Correspondence; Landon family -- Archives; Landon, Henry; Landon, Jared; Landon, Samuel, ca. 1700-1782?; Long Island Railroad Company.; Sage, Ebenezer, 1755-1834 -- Correspondence; Seaflower (Sloop: ca. 1786).; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 48th (1861-1865). -- Correspondence; Accounts; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Suffolk County; Articles of incorporation.; Commerce; Correspondence; County courts |z New York (State) |z Suffolk County; Cutchogue (N.Y.); Daybooks; Deeds; Diaries; Estate inventories.; Executors and administrators |z New York (State) |z Suffolk County; Genealogy; Indentures; Indians of North America |v Treaties.; Judges |z New York (State) |z Suffolk County; Ledgers (account books); Legal documents; legal instruments; Liquor laws |z New York (State) |z Suffolk County; Long Island (N.Y.) |x History |y Revolution, 1775-1783; Petitions; Politics, Practical |z New York (State) |z Suffolk County; Promissory notes; Receipts (financial records); Southold (N.Y.); Suffolk County (N.Y.); Warrants
- Series 1: Legal Files., 1665-1862; 1.0 Linear feet
  Arrangement note
  Legal Files is arranged by broad subject area. Folders holding a broad mix of Suffolk County and then Southold town matters are followed by more narrowly-defined subjects. Miscellaneous materials close the series.
  Users of the collection should be aware that it was not possible during processing to relate all individual documents on the basis of specific matters (e.g., to bring together all documents for a particular estate or court case). Therefore, it is possible that documents for particular matters will be found in various folders of the series.
  Users should also be aware that many documents seem to be drafts, with each document referencing multiple matters. A folder of miscellaneous material at the end of the series includes material that could not be categorized or that had matters so divergent as to preclude a single categorization.
  Scope and Contents note
  Legal Files is comprised principally of the records of Henry Landon in his various official capacities, such as justice of the peace in Suffolk County (circa 1820s-1850s); estates executor; officer of an incorporated religious society in Cutchogue; and officer in Southold's Democratic-Republican party. The series also includes documents related to Jared Landon's tenure as justice of the peace in the late 1700s and early 1800s. Some documents pertain to the Landons' personal legal matters, including a case concerning Henry and Samuel H. Landon (and, after his death, Samuel's estate) related to land takings for the Long Island Railroad. Much of the material appears to consist of drafts, copies, or transcriptions.
  Document forms in the series that relate to court matters include court filings, court orders, decisions, testimony, subpoenas, complaints, trespasses on cases, proxies, witness statements, deeds, indentures, and wills and other estate execution papers. Court cases primarily concern matters of indebtedness, but also include theft, assault, rape, fraud, bastardy, and murder.
  Southold town matters represented in the series include local elections, indentures for the overseers of the poor, town meetings, public notices, extracts from town records, judgments, and petitions against liquor licensing. Southold Democratic-Republican party matters include notices of meetings, delegate elections, and resolutions concerning national political events.
  There are several corporate matters represented in the series, including dividend announcements and other documents from various whaling and fishing ventures, and draft articles of incorporation for the artillery company under the command of Capt. Silas Horton, the Education Society of Southold, the Moral Society of Southold, and the Suffolk County Anti-Slavery Society.
  The series includes legal matters related to the American Revolution. These include complaints from Flushing farmers recorded against one Col. Archibald Hamilton during the war, records of takings of oxen and other property, and post-war pension claims.
  The series includes various documents with reference to African-Americans. Those identified during processing include court cases in which African-Americans were charged with attempted rape, burglary, and larceny, as well as cases in which African-Americans appear as witnesses and seek relief from a (presumably white) man who imposed himself on a family. In addition, African-Americans appear as debtors to Dr. Tuthill's estate, members of Cutchogue's religious society, and a wagon driver (in connection with the complaints against Col. Hamilton).
  Although the bulk of the series concerns Suffolk County and Southold in particular, there is a set of miscellaneous legal documents from the 1700s concerning other jurisdictions in New York, Connecticut, New Jersey, Rhode Island, and Virginia. Among the more notable New York documents are a 1793 Flatbush land indenture, a circa 1730 deed of trust in favor of a Presbyterian Church in Manhattan, and a 1794 assault complaint by a Brooklyn (Gowanus) resident.
  - Suffolk County Court Orders (1 of 2)., 1772; 1784-1812 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Suffolk County Court Orders (2 of 2)., 1833-1855 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Suffolk County Court Matters (1 of 4)., 1814-1840 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Suffolk County Court Matters (2 of 4)., 1841-1844 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Suffolk County Court Matters (3 of 4)., 1844-1862 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Suffolk County Court Matters (4 of 4)., circa 1840s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Suffolk County Land Matters (1 of 2)., 1667-1850 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Suffolk County Land Matters (2 of 2)., circa 1790-1850 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Suffolk County School District Matters., 1813-1858 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Southold Town Matters (1 of 2)., 1665-1856 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Southold Town Matters (2 of 2)., circa 1830-1850 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Legal Matters - Jared Landon., 1767-1811 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Legal Matters - Henry Landon., 1823-1843 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Estate and Other Matters - Samuel H. Landon., 1825-1852 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Estate Matters - Dr. Sylvester Tuthill., 1840-1844 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Estate Matters - Lorenzo Case., 1848-1853 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Estate Matters - Other., 1737-1854 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Commercial Matters - Whaling and Fishing Companies., 1834-1853 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Corporate Documents - Artillery Company; Anti-Slavery, Education, and Moral Societies., 1815-1820 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Liquor Licensing and Opposition - Southold., 1832-1845 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Religious Society of Cutchogue., 1742-1858 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - American Revolution War Claims and Pensions., 1779-1835 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Complaints Against Col. Archibald Hamilton., 1779-1780 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Indentures and Agreements., 1722-1793 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Court Case Documents., 1726-1795 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Legal Documents., 1831-1851 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Series 2: Correspondence., 1777-1864; 0.25 Linear feet
  Correspondence to or from a Landon appears first in the series. The exchanges between Jared and Samuel are foldered by recipient. Landon correspondence is followed by correspondence to or from other or unknown correspondents, which is arranged chronologically. Much of the correspondence in this latter set likely includes correspondence sent to a Landon, especially Henry, though that is not explicit on the face of it.
  The bulk of Correspondence is directed to Henry Landon concerning various legal, business, political, and New York State legislative matters. Among the letters to Henry concerning national political affairs are those from U.S. Congressmen Abel Huntington (1834) and Charles A. Floyd (1842). Among the letters concerning local political and legislative matters is an 1847 letter from the Sag Harbor trustees to Henry, in his capacity as State Assemblyman, proposing legislative amendments to Sag Harbor's act of incorporation. Correspondence concerning Landon's dealings with the Long Island Rail Road in connection with land acquisition is in the series.
  The series also includes correspondence between Jared Landon and his father, Samuel, from the period in which Samuel was a refugee in Connecticut during the British occupation of New York City. The series includes Jared's 1778 petition for release from military prison. Several pieces refer to wartime hardships on Long Island. Other correspondence to Jared includes an 1814 letter from U.S. Congressman Ebenezer Sage in which Sage expresses his fear that Britain intends to recolonize America.
  Other correspondents include, among others, Phineas Corey, David Conkling, Stephen Conkling, Joshua Fleet, and Daniel Osborn. The series includes correspondence of 1862-63 to Colonel W.B. Barton, commander of the 48th Regiment of New York State Volunteers in South Carolina, from Confederate commanders regarding movements under flags of truce. An 1836 document to Henry describes the facts of a case to be decided in which an African-American girl of about 10, originally bound by her mother to a Mr. Smith, sought to remain bound to Smith, rather than be taken away by her brothers upon the death of her mother. The series also includes an undated circular letter from "The Ladies" giving playful encouragement to the public speaking endeavors of the "Younger Members" of the Cutchogue Young Men's Debating Society. In addition to the commercial, legal, and political matters that predominate in the series, some of the correspondence is also concerned, at least in part, with matters of health and religious fervor.
  - Landon, Samuel., 1777-1780 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Landon, Jared., 1778-1814 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Notable Correspondent
    Folder includes an 1814 item from U.S. Congressman Ebenezer Sage.
  - Landon, Henry (1 of 2)., 1805-1836 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Folder includes an 1814 item from U.S. Congressman Abel Huntington.
  - Landon, Henry (2 of 2)., 1840-1863 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Notable Correspondents
    Folder includes an 1842 item from U.S. Congressman Charles A. Floyd.
  - Other Landon., 1839-1843 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Other and Unknown Correspondents (1 of 4)., 1718-1788 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Other and Unknown Correspondents (2 of 4)., 1804-1848 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Other and Unknown Correspondents (3 of 4)., 1852-1864 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Other and Unknown Correspondents (4 of 4)., circa 1780-1850 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series 3: Financial Records., 1759-1864; 1.0 Linear feet
  The series proceeds in rough chronological order. Folders containing documents explicitly related to Conkling matters are labeled as such. Folders labeled as miscellaneous likely hold Conkling-related material (as well as other matters), but the documents are not clear in this regard. Similarly, material explicitly linked to Henry Landon are in folders labeled accordingly. Folders that contain financial material likely related to Henry Landon indicate his name in [brackets].
  Financial Records generally consists of material from the late 1700s that concerns estate cases handled by Jared Landon and from circa 1820-1860 that concerns various financial matters of Henry Landon. Formats include day books, ledgers, vendue (auction) accounts, inventories, promissory notes, account statements, receipts, invoices, sales agreements, and the like.
  For the late 1700s, the series consists of an extensive set of business and estate settlement records for merchant David Conkling of Southold, deceased 1787. Records of two other Conklings, Stephen and Joseph, are also found with David's estate records, for which Jared Landon and Stephen were co-executors. There are several account books (i.e., day books, ledgers, journals) in the series; although most cannot be directly traced to an owner, it is possible that some of these relate to David Conkling. Conkling-related documents include those concerning the Conkling-owned sloop Seaflower.
  Other financial records from the late 1700s and early 1800s likely concern Jared Landon personally or were related to other professional matters he worked on, but these are less clear and less extensive than material directly associated with the Conklings. Among these documents is a 1790 receipt for a subscription to the Gazette of the United States, signed by John Fenno.
  The material holds several documents related to African-Americans. Various day books, journals, and transaction documents contain references to African-Americans executing transactions on behalf of others or for themselves, including transactions with the Conkling estate. The series includes a 1793 levy from a collector indicating that a "negro boy" would be taken in partial payment of an assessment for street improvements.
  From circa 1820 to 1860, the series includes extensive financial records of Henry Landon. These records primarily concern his personal affairs, most notably a detailed account book for the period 1815 to 1853. The miscellaneous financial documents consist of standalone items whose salient features consist of calculations, accounts, and other numbers-oriented notes. Records of expenses incurred on travel, weights of hogs, value of fish taken, bushels of produce, and other such data can be found in Henry's records.
  - Day Book (Sundry Goods)., 1767-1768 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Ledger - Letter B., 1769-1772 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Ledger - Letter C., 1767-1772 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Account Book - Flaxseed (and Sundry)., 1782-1787 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Day Book (Sundry Goods)., 1784-1787 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Day Book - Oysterponds (Rum, etc.)., 1784-1787 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Account Books., 1787 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Receipts and Promissory Note Book - Conkling., 1784-1793 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Vendue Book - David Conkling Estate., 1787-1802 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Inventories - Conkling., 1779-1787 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Promissory Notes; Transaction Authorizations - Conkling., 1766-1791 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Account Statements - Conkling., 1770-1788 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Transaction Receipts - Conkling (1 of 3)., 1784-1787 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Transaction Receipts - Conkling (2 of 3)., 1769-1788 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Transaction Receipts - Conkling (3 of 3)., 1784-1789 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Cargo Records - Sloop Seaflower - Conkling., 1784-1788 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Financial (1 of 2)., 1759-1801 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Includes a receipt for subscription to the Gazette of the United States, signed by John Fenno.
  - Miscellaneous Financial (2 of 2)., circa 1780-1800 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Day Book (Sundry Goods)., 1798-1799 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Debtor Journal., circa 1800 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Day Book - W.H. Cook (?)., 1825 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Ledger., 1825 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Account Book - Henry Landon., 1815-1853 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Personal Financial - Henry Landon., 1823-1864 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Financial - Henry Landon., 1823-1845 (Box 5, Folder 8)